<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
	<element name="Lotol" type="Race" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACE_LOTOL">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">Creatures of swamp, river, and lake, these salamander-kin go with the flow—literally. Where the water wends, lotol make their home. Despite their shorter lives, lotol rarely rush; they have little to prove and trust in the currents of fate to take them where they need to be. Masters of adaptation, it is the lotol’s propensity to find joy in the all things that sets them apart from other races: the croak of a bullfrog, the death of an elder, or the sweet scent of petrichor after a long hot summer; all are accepted with an open, wholesome grace.</p>
			<h4>LIZARD LEGEND</h4>
			<p>In lotol legend, the first lotol ancestor, Ablon the Stoney, had magnificently hard scales, but was a stoic and unfeeling creature. To teach him a lesson, the great Platinum Dragon cursed him to be more sensitive. Ablon’s scales fell from his body, and his kin would forever bear this soft-skinned nature as a reminder to always be aware of how your actions might affect the world around you. In their own tongue, lotol are known as the ‘lizards without scales’.</p>
			<p class="indent">Consequently, lotol always remark when they meet humanoids that do have scales, such as dragonborn, lizardfolk, or golin. This reaction varies, from awe to envy, or from open infatuation to a fearful expectation of insensitivity or brutishness (stereotypes some lotol individuals hold). A sect of lotol, The Platinum Apology, dedicate their lives to ending this curse and restoring themselves as scale-wearing reptiles. Whether or not this curse is real, let alone possible, is unknown.</p>
			<h4>WATER WADERS</h4>
			<p>The few times lotol ever come into conflict with neighbours, it is almost always to do with water. A growing lotol population creates new wetlands by damming up rivers, sometimes to the chagrin of local trappers and woodsfolk. Following floods, whole pods of lotol can find themselves washed downstream into an entirely new (and often recently-drowned) habitat. Fortunately for those that may be reconstructing their lives following such an inundation, lotol are more than keen to help. Lotol with innate aqueous adaptations can prove a blessing to washed out villages and can more than offset the enmity villagers may feel towards this newly-arrived population of semi-nomadic salamander-folk.</p>
			<p class="indent">With their supple, permeable skin, lotol are extremely sensitive to pollutants. If a black dragon poisons the water upstream of them or heavy metals from a dwarven mine begin to leech into the groundwater, lotol are often the first to know. The only record of lotol going to war is recorded in the oral chant <i>The Cleansing Tide</i>. With the help of a bronze dragon, Chionthan the Forgetful, lotol of the Chion Valley snuck upon the cruel and pernicious Ulvik the Black and delivered a mighty electric current into his lair, causing him to flee in fear. Lotol believe that their ability to generate electric currents through their skin is a blessing from the great Chionthan.</p>
			<h4>ADAPTIVE AND ATYPICAL</h4>
			<p>To call lotol adaptive is an understatement. When required, lotol can change their very physiology, growing gills, improving their eyesight, or even developing long, elastic tongues. Adapting quickly to different environments allows them to explore a gamut of potential habitats, despite their sensitive skin. Some lotol even embark on quests, seeking to put themselves in the most unusual and atypical situations imaginable in order to unlock as-yet-undiscovered adaptations.</p>
			<h4>LOTOL TRAITS</h4>
			<p>As a lotol, you have the following racial traits.</p>
			<span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Wisdom score increases by 2, and your Constitution score increases by 1.<br />
			<span class="feature">Age.</span>Newborn lotol metamorphose into their adult form in 1 year and reach full maturity after 10 years. They typically live between 40 and 50 years.<br /> 
			<span class="feature">Size.</span>Lotol never stop growing; the larger the lotol, the older it probably is! Lotol typically range from 4 feet to 5 feet tall. Your size is Medium.<br />
			<span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is <b>30 feet.</b><br />
			<span class="feature">Oblivious.</span>You have <b>advantage</b> on Wisdom saving throws.<br />
			<span class="feature">Slippery Skin.</span>You have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to prevent or end the <b>grappled</b> and/or <b>restrained</b> conditions on yourself.<br />
			<span class="feature">Languages.</span>You can speak, read, and write Common and one other language of your choice.<br />
			<span class="feature">Adaptive Polymorphism.</span>Each lotol’s lineage is unique, and certain traits follow clans or families, or mutate by chance in individuals. Choose two of the following adaptations. When you gain a level, you can choose to replace one of these adaptations with another over the course of your next long rest:<br />
			<ul>
				<li><b>Aqueous Adaptation.</b> You gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed and can breathe underwater.<br /></li>
				<li><b>Gecko Cling.</b> You gain a climbing speed of <b>20 feet</b> and you have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to maintain grapples and prevent yourself being disarmed of an object you are holding.</li>
				<li><b>Darkvision.</b> Accustomed to life in the murky underbrush, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within <b>60 feet</b> of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</li>
				<li><b>Prehensile Tongue.</b>Your long, extendable tongue can be used to grab Tiny objects out of arm’s reach. As a bonus action, you can use your tongue to grab a Tiny object within <b>20 feet</b> of you. If the object weighs less than 10 pounds, isn’t being worn or carried, and isn’t fixed to any surface, you pull the object back to you.</li>
				<li><b>Shocking Skin.</b>You learn the <i>shocking grasp</i> cantrip. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this spell. When a creature within <b>5 feet</b> of you hits you with a melee attack, you can use a reaction to cast the <i>shocking grasp</i> cantrip, targeting the attacker. After you cast the spell in this way, you can’t do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="2" />
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_OBLIVIOUS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_SLIPPERY_SKIN" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_ADAPTIVE_POLYMORPHISM" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Lotol)" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Oblivious" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_OBLIVIOUS">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Wisdom saving throws.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantage on Wisdom saving throws.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Slippery Skin" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_SLIPPERY_SKIN">
		<description>
			<p>You have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to prevent or end the <b>grappled</b> and/or <b>restrained</b> conditions on yourself.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to prevent or end the <b>grappled</b> and/or <b>restrained</b> conditions on yourself.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Adaptive Polymorphism" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_ADAPTIVE_POLYMORPHISM">
		<description>
			<p>Each lotol’s lineage is unique, and certain traits follow clans or families, or mutate by chance in individuals. Choose two of the following adaptations. When you gain a level, you can choose to replace one of these adaptations with another over the course of your next long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Each lotol’s lineage is unique, and certain traits follow clans or families, or mutate by chance in individuals.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Adaptive Polymorphism 1" supports="Adaptive Polymorphism" level="1" />
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Adaptive Polymorphism 2" supports="Adaptive Polymorphism" level="1" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Aqueous Adaptation" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_LOTOL_AQUEOUS_ADAPTATION">
		<meta>
			<parent>Lotol</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Adaptive Polymorphism</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed and can breathe underwater.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can breathe under water.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:swim" value="30" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Darkvision" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_LOTOL_DARKVISION">
		<meta>
			<parent>Lotol</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Adaptive Polymorphism</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Accustomed to life in the murky underbrush, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within <b>60 feet</b> of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Gecko Cling" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_LOTOL_GECKO_CLING">
		<meta>
			<parent>Lotol</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Adaptive Polymorphism</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You gain a climbing speed of <b>20 feet</b> and you have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to maintain grapples and prevent yourself being disarmed of an object you are holding.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have <b>advantage</b> on ability checks and saving throws made to maintain grapples and prevent yourself being disarmed of an object you are holding.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:climb" value="20" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Prehensile Tongue" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_LOTOL_PREHENSILE_TONGUE">
		<meta>
			<parent>Lotol</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Adaptive Polymorphism</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your long, extendable tongue can be used to grab Tiny objects out of arm’s reach. As a bonus action, you can use your tongue to grab a Tiny object within <b>20 feet</b> of you. If the object weighs less than 10 pounds, isn’t being worn or carried, and isn’t fixed to any surface, you pull the object back to you.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>As a bonus action, you can use your tongue to grab a Tiny object within <b>20 feet</b> of you. If the object weighs less than 10 pounds, isn’t being worn or carried, and isn’t fixed to any surface, you pull the object back to you.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Shocking Skin" type="Racial Trait" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_RACIAL_TRAIT_LOTOL_SHOCKING_SKIN">
		<meta>
			<parent>Lotol</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Adaptive Polymorphism</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You learn the <i>shocking grasp</i> cantrip. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this spell. When a creature within <b>5 feet</b> of you hits you with a melee attack, you can use a reaction to cast the <i>shocking grasp</i> cantrip, targeting the attacker. After you cast the spell in this way, you can’t do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When a creature within <b>5 feet</b> of you hits you with a melee attack, you can use a reaction to cast the <i>shocking grasp</i> cantrip, targeting the attacker.  After you cast the spell in this way, you can’t do so again until you finish a short or long rest. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for this spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
</elements>