<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
	<element name="College of Fleshweaving" type="Archetype" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_BARD_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING">
		<meta>
			<parent>Bard</parent>
		</meta>
		<supports>Bard College</supports>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;If leather is a material, then why not skin itself? Students of the College of Fleshweaving make works of art out of weeping wounds, transform disfigurement into displays of transcendent beauty, and mould flesh into innovative adaptations inspired by the flora and fauna around them. A fleshweaver bard down on their luck might find employment as a battlefield surgeon, while the epitome of a fleshweaver’s career is to be the chief facemaker to royalty, altering their visage and physiology through biomantic rituals and deft needlework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div element="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_MALLEABLE_VISAGE" /&gt;
&lt;div element="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SUTURER" /&gt;
&lt;div element="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_RITUAL_RESKIN" /&gt;
&lt;div element="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SOULSEW" /&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_MALLEABLE_VISAGE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SUTURER" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_RITUAL_RESKIN" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SOULSEW" level="14" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Malleable Visage" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_MALLEABLE_VISAGE">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;Years spent mending, shaping, and adapting flesh have given you a preternatural ability to modify your own body. You are proficient with surgeon’s tools, which you can use as a spellcasting focus, and you know the alter self spell, which counts as a bard spell for you, but it doesn’t count against the number of bard spells you know. Over the course of 1 minute, you can cast the spell without expending a spell slot, choosing only the Change Appearance option. When you cast the spell in this way, it doesn’t require concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="indent"&gt;In addition, over the course of 10 minutes, you can use your surgeon’s tools to change the appearance of a willing creature. It magically gains the benefits of the Change Appearance effect of the alter self spell, which lasts until it finishes a long rest. After you use your surgeon’s tools in this way, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Over the course of 1 minute, you can cast Alter Self the spell without expending a spell slot, choosing only the Change Appearance option. When you cast the spell in this way, it doesn’t require concentration.
    In addition, over the course of 10 minutes, you can use your surgeon’s tools to change the appearance of a willing creature. It magically gains the benefits of the Change Appearance effect of the Alter Self spell, which lasts until it finishes a long rest. After you use your surgeon’s tools in this way, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_TOOL_PROFICIENCY_SURGEONS_TOOLS" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_ALTER_SELF" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Suturer" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SUTURER">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;You know the spiritual weapon spell, which is a bard spell for you, but doesn’t count against the number of spells you know. You can cast this spell once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a long rest. When you cast it as a bard spell, the weapon takes the form of a giant needle and thread, and deals piercing damage instead of force damage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="indent"&gt;You also learn different ways to use this spiritual weapon. You gain the Suture benefit below, and you gain an additional benefit below when you reach 5th level and 10th level in this class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Suture (3rd Level).&lt;/b&gt; As a bonus action or an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and grant temporary hit points equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die to one creature within 5 feet of the weapon. If the creature has 0 hit points, you can stabilise it, instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Unspool (5th Level).&lt;/b&gt; As an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and force one creature within 5 feet of the weapon to make a Strength saving throw against your bard spell save DC.On a failure, magical threads wrap around the creature, which is restrained for 1 minute. The target can use its action to repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on a success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Acupuncture (10th Level).&lt;/b&gt; As an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and make a melee spell attack against one creature within 5 feet of it. On a hit, the creature takes piercing damage equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus your Charisma modifier, and must make a Constitution saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, the creature is paralysed until the end of its next turn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You can cast Spiritual Weapon once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a long rest. When you cast it as a bard spell, the weapon takes the form of a giant needle and thread, and deals piercing damage instead of force damage.
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;You also learn different ways to use this spiritual weapon. You gain the Suture benefit below, and you gain an additional benefit below when you reach 5th level and 10th level in this class.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SUTURE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_UNSPOOL" level="5" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_ACUPUNCTURE" level="10" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SPIRITUAL_WEAPON" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Suture" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SUTURE">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;As a bonus action or an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and grant temporary hit points equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die to one creature within 5 feet of the weapon. If the creature has 0 hit points, you can stabilise it, instead.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action or Bonus Action">
			<description>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and grant temporary hit points equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die to one creature within 5 feet of the weapon. If the creature has 0 hit points, you can stabilise it, instead.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Unspool" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_UNSPOOL">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;As an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and force one creature within 5 feet of the weapon to make a Strength saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, magical threads wrap around the creature, which is restrained for 1 minute. The target can use its action to repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on a success.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and force one creature within 5 feet of the weapon to make a Strength saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, magical threads wrap around the creature, which is restrained for 1 minute. The target can use its action to repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on a success.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Acupuncture" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_ACUPUNCTURE">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;As an action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and make a melee spell attack against one creature within 5 feet of it. On a hit, the creature takes piercing damage equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus your Charisma modifier, and must make a Constitution saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, the creature is paralysed until the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Action">
			<description>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and make a melee spell attack against one creature within 5 feet of it. On a hit, the creature takes piercing damage equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus your Charisma modifier, and must make a Constitution saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, the creature is paralysed until the end of its next turn.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Ritual Reskin" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_RITUAL_RESKIN">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;Over the course of &lt;b&gt;10 minutes&lt;/b&gt;, you can perform a surgical ritual on creatures that you can see within &lt;b&gt;60 feet&lt;/b&gt; of you (including yourself), up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). The creatures gain one of the following adaptations for the next &lt;b&gt;hour&lt;/b&gt;. You choose one adaptation to affect all creatures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bull’s Buns.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Strength&lt;/b&gt; checks, and counts as one size larger when determining its carrying capacity and the weight it can push, drag, or lift.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cactus Skin.&lt;/b&gt; The target is covered in razor-sharp spikes. At the end of each of the target’s turns, each creature grappling it must make a &lt;b&gt;Constitution saving throw&lt;/b&gt; against your &lt;b&gt;bard spell save DC&lt;/b&gt;. On a failure, a creature takes piercing damage equal to your Bardic Inspiration die and releases the target from its grapple. On a success, a creature takes half as much damage and doesn’t have to release the target.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cat’s Paws.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; &lt;b&gt;on Dexterity&lt;/b&gt; checks. It also doesn’t take damage from falling &lt;b&gt;20 feet&lt;/b&gt; or less if it isn’t incapacitated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Fish Form.&lt;/b&gt; The target can breathe underwater and gains a swimming speed equal to its walking speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Owl’s Sight.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Wisdom&lt;/b&gt; checks and initiative rolls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rhino’s Hide.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Constitution&lt;/b&gt; checks and gains temporary hit points equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus you Charisma modifier (minimum 1), which are lost when the effect ends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you use this feature, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use this feature again.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet action="10 minutes">
			<description>You can perform a surgical ritual on creatures that you can see within 60 feet of you (including yourself), up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature).  You choose one adaptation to affect all creatures. (See spell cards for further detail, cantrips).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_HGTMH_SPELL_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_RITUAL_RESKIN" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="*Ritual Reskin" type="Spell" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_SPELL_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_RITUAL_RESKIN">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;Over the course of &lt;b&gt;10 minutes&lt;/b&gt;, you can perform a surgical ritual on creatures that you can see within &lt;b&gt;60 feet&lt;/b&gt; of you (including yourself), up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). The creatures gain one of the following adaptations for the next &lt;b&gt;hour&lt;/b&gt;. You choose one adaptation to affect all creatures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;• Bull’s Buns.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Strength&lt;/b&gt; checks, and counts as one size larger when determining its carrying capacity and the weight it can push, drag, or lift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;• Cactus Skin.&lt;/b&gt; The target is covered in razor-sharp spikes. At the end of each of the target’s turns, each creature grappling it must make a &lt;b&gt;Constitution saving throw&lt;/b&gt; against your &lt;b&gt;bard spell save DC&lt;/b&gt;. On a failure, a creature takes piercing damage equal to your Bardic Inspiration die and releases the target from its grapple. On a success, a creature takes half as much damage and doesn’t have to release the target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;• Cat’s Paws.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; &lt;b&gt;on Dexterity&lt;/b&gt; checks. It also doesn’t take damage from falling &lt;b&gt;20 feet&lt;/b&gt; or less if it isn’t incapacitated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;• Fish Form.&lt;/b&gt; The target can breathe underwater and gains a swimming speed equal to its walking speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;• Owl’s Sight.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Wisdom&lt;/b&gt; checks and initiative rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;• Rhino’s Hide.&lt;/b&gt; The target has &lt;b&gt;advantage&lt;/b&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Constitution&lt;/b&gt; checks and gains temporary hit points equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus you Charisma modifier (minimum 1), which are lost when the effect ends.
&lt;p&gt;After you use this feature, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use this feature again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to move the weapon up to 20 feet and make a melee spell attack against one creature within 5 feet of it. On a hit, the creature takes piercing damage equal to one roll of your Bardic Inspiration die plus your Charisma modifier, and must make a Constitution saving throw against your bard spell save DC. On a failure, the creature is paralysed until the end of its next turn.&lt;p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">10 minutes</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">60 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent"></set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Soulsew" type="Archetype Feature" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SOULSEW">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;When a creature uses one of your Bardic Inspiration dice, or fails a saving throw against your Suturer feature’s Unspool or Acupuncture effects, it becomes ‘soulsewn’ to you for &lt;b&gt;1 minute&lt;/b&gt;. While soulsewn, an ethereal thread connects you to this creature via a straight line that only you and creatures with truesight can see. This thread breaks if the creature is ever more than &lt;b&gt;100 feet&lt;/b&gt; away from you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p class="indent"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spool.&lt;/b&gt; You can use a bonus action to teleport to the nearest unoccupied space of a soulsewn creature of your choice, or attempt to switch places with a soulsewn creature. If the creature is unwilling to switch places, you must succeed on a contested &lt;b&gt;Charisma&lt;/b&gt; check against the creature. On a success, or if the creature is willing, you and the target telepport, switching places with one another. If there is not enough space for either of you to switch places, you automatically lose the contest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p class="indent"&gt;You can teleport using this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum 1), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When a creature uses one of your Bardic Inspiration dice, or fails a saving throw against your Suturer feature’s Unspool or Acupuncture effects, it becomes ‘soulsewn’ to you for 1 minute. While soulsewn, an ethereal thread connects you to this creature via a straight line that only you and creatures with truesight can see. This thread breaks if the creature is ever more than 100 feet away from you.
(Further details are in the spell cards, see Spool cantrip).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_HGTMH_SPELL_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SPOOL" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="*Spool" type="Spell" source="Heliana’s Guide to Monster Hunting" id="ID_HGTMH_SPELL_COLLEGE_OF_FLESHWEAVING_SPOOL">
		<meta>
			<parent>College of Fleshweaving</parent>
		</meta>
		<description>
			<html>&lt;p&gt;You can use a bonus action to teleport to the nearest unoccupied space of a soulsewn creature of your choice, or attempt to switch places with a soulsewn creature. If the creature is unwilling to switch places, you must succeed on a contested &lt;b&gt;Charisma&lt;/b&gt; check against the creature. On a success, or if the creature is willing, you and the target telepport, switching places with one another. If there is not enough space for either of you to switch places, you automatically lose the contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="indent"&gt;You can teleport using this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum 1), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.&lt;/p&gt;</html>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">100 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent"></set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
</elements>